Okay
בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is ע"ט, Ayin Tet, זבחים
Zvachim 79. We pick up in the middle of ע"ט עמוד א',
Ayin Tet Amud Aleph, about six seven lines down, which is a
short דף, daf, so basically half the way down with the asterisk,
אמר רבא. Amar Rava. And just for context, you know what we'd
been discussing is issues relating to ביטול, Bitul, classic ביטול Bitul discussions,
מין במינו, Min BeMino, like and like, and מין בשאינו מינו, Min
Be'eino Mino, like and and not like. So first we have the
very important position of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, אין דם מבטל דם,
Ein Dam Mevatel Dam, which is basically a principle that מין במינו
לא בטיל, Min BeMino Lo Batel, that like and like is never
בטיל, batel, blood and blood, it's all blood. טריפה Traife chicken soup
mixed up with כשר kosher chicken soup, it's all chicken soup, it's
all chicken, it's all the same. If there's no difference, it can't
lose its identity. It's always present. Actually there's a position of רש"י
Rashi that we rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, thank God that
is not the actual accepted פסק. psak. So that's the position of
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, we rule like the חכמים Chachamim that מין
במינו Min BeMino is בטיל batel fundamentally with רוב, rov, with a
majority. However, if it is מין בשאינו מינו, Min Be'eino Mino, like
in non-like, then the principle is, at least for foods, we haven't
said this yet, but we're about to, but we haven't said it
yet in the גמרא, Gemara, the principle at least for food is
that it goes בטיל, batel, if it can be tasted, נותן טעם,
Notein Ta'am, then it is discernible and therefore it is not בטיל.
batel. And in the case that we have seen dealing with, you
know, blood getting mixed up with water, with wine, when it's not
about food but it's about, you know, all other areas and, and
our case specifically about putting it on the מזבח, Mizbeach, you know,
using it as a קרבן, Korban, then it doesn't go by taste,
it goes by, by appearance. If you can detect the presence of
blood, then it isn't בטיל, batel, and in our case by קרבנות,
Korbanot, that's actually good. If it's not בטיל, batel, you can throw
it on the מזבח. Mizbeach. So this is actually a case where
you want something to not be בטיל. batel. And the last thing
we dealt with, which is quite a חידוש, Chiddush, and the גמרא
Gemara never sort of laid down clear parameters, is that even if
the blood gets mixed up with wine, or with other blood, you
would use the lenient position of being not בטיל, batel, imagining it
was אינו מינו. Eino Mino. You know, when you're dealing with איסור,
Issur, you know, so you got a little חזיר Chazir falls into
your
טריפה traife chicken soup from a non-shechted chicken into your כשר kosher
chicken soup, you don't say, oh, it goes by רוב. rov. You
say if it had been something that tasted different, you could taste
it one in sixty, so it's not בטיל, batel, anything less than
one in sixty, even though it's all the same. There you are
being strict and imagining it in a case of אינו מינו. Eino
Mino. But here we're going to be lenient even though you cannot
discern the blood, it is קרבן Korban blood getting mixed up with
other blood, or getting mixed up with wine, and it cannot be
discerned, nevertheless since in an אינו מינו Eino Mino case, had it
been water it could be discerned, it's not בטיל batel and you
can still throw it on the מזבח. Mizbeach. That is quite, quite
shocking that you can do that to be lenient. And we'll just
read the end of the
תוספות Tosafot here on ע"ט עמוד א', Ayin Tet Amud Aleph, it
started from the previous דף, daf, and this is the תוספות Tosafot
where he says like this, he says, about ten lines before the
lines get to be the medium sized, ten lines of the narrow
lines that run alongside the גמרא, Gemara, from the bottom of those
narrow lines where תוספות Tosafot says וצריך לדקדק, v'tzarich ledakdek, the line
starts with the word רואין, ro'in, וצריך לדקדק מאי שנא גבי קדשים
וטומאה ומקוה אמרינן רואין הכא ובמכות וגבי איסורא לא אמרינן רואין אלא
מין במינו דאורייתא ברובא.
v'tzarich ledakdek mai shna gabei kodshin v'tumah u'mikvah amrinan
ro'in hacha u'bmakkos v'gabei issura lo amrinan ro'in ela min bemino d'oraita
beruba. How come here we say we imagine it to be a
case of אינו מינו Eino Mino and we're actually, you know, going
to be even sometimes lenient, and normally we would say מין במינו
Min BeMino is
בטיל batel ברוב berov and maybe we could be strict against it
but not to be lenient against it? וגבי טומאה נמי איכא דוקתא
דלא אמרינן רואין v'gabei tumah nami ika duktei d'lo amrinan ro'in וגבי
etc. etc., so
אלא and if you look at the first of the medium lines
of תוספות, Tosafot, היכא דאיתמר איתמר היכא דלא איתמר לא איתמר, heicha
d'itmar itmar heicha d'lo itmar lo itmar, okay, and so where it
was said it was said, where it wasn't it wasn't, which basically
means we do not know the reasons, we don't know principles. Okay,
but here it is quite surprising that even though it's מין במינו
Min BeMino and it should be בטיל, batel, you use the רואין
ro'in to be lenient and to allow it to be said as
the blood is still present. Okay, so that's where we wrapped up
yesterday. Now we pick up with אמר רבא. Amar Rava. אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, again the asterisk about eight lines down in the גמרא,
Gemara, אמר רבא זימנין אמרי רבנן בטעמא וזימנין אמרי רבנן ברובא וזימנין
אמרי רבנן בחזותא. Amar Rava: Zimnin amri Rabbanan b'ta'ama v'zimnin amri Rabbanan
b'ruba v'zimnin amri Rabbanan b'chazuta. See? So it's a nice summary of
what I just said. The rabbis sometimes say you go by taste,
they sometimes say you go by majority, and they sometimes say you
go by appearances. מין בשאינו מינו, Min Be'she'eino Mino, if it is
like and unlike, בטעמא, be'ta'ama, then you go by taste, right? That
is a drop of
חזיר Chazir soup falls into your chicken soup. So it, if it
can be tasted, it's not בטיל, batel, once it cannot be tasted,
it is בטיל. batel. Okay. מין במינו ברובא, Min b'mino b'rova, if
it's like and like, a drop of non-kosher chicken soup because the
chicken wasn't שחט shachted falls into your kosher chicken soup, that is
בטל batel by רוב, rov, by the majority. At least מדאורייתא, m'dioraita,
it is בטל batel by רוב. rov. So תוספות Tosafot says we're
clearly talking about דאורייתא. dioraita. דרבנן, derabbanan, you need שישים; shishim; we
all know that rule of one in sixty. But at the דאורייתא
dioraita level, you go by
רוב. rov. והיכא דאיכא חזותא במרא, V'heicha d'ika chazuta b'mora, and where
there are appearances, it goes by appearances. Now, what do you mean
where there are appearances? Everything always has an appearance. So if you
take a look at רש"י, Rashi, והיכא דאיכא חזותא, v'heicha d'ika chazuta,
רש"י Rashi says, מידי דלא תלי בטעמא, midi d'lo tali b'tama, when
it's not about taste, when it's not about forbidden food and therefore
the focus is on taste. So anything else in the world, as
we said the other day, it goes by appearance. Appearance is the
fundamental sense in which we, sight for sighted people, in which they
experience the world, and therefore its presence is determined by whether it
is visible when it is not an issue or discernible when it
is not an issue of taste. מידי דלא תלי בטעמא אלא בחזותא
כגון לעניין טבילת מקוה בחזותא. Midi d'lo tali b'tama ella b'chazuta k'gon
l'inyan tvilat mikva b'chazuta. Okay, so when it's not about taste, you
go by can it visibly be discernible? When it is about taste,
you go can it be tasted? That's מין באינו מינו. min b'eino
mino. And when it is מין במינו, min b'mino, you go by
majority. Okay, and as I said, תוספות Tosafot points out that this
is דאורייתא dioraita because דרבנן, derabbanan, of course, מין במינו min b'mino
you would need sixty. And by the way, just to say one
sentence about this huge תוספות, Tosafot, אמרי רבנן בטעמא, amri rabbanan b'tama,
that although רש"י, Rashi, as I said, is very strict and says
מין במינו min b'mino we rule like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda it's
not בטל. batel. רש"י Rashi on the other hand says that the
whole principle of טעם כעיקר, ta'am k'ikar, that if something can be
tasted it's like it's still present, רש"י Rashi says that's only דרבנן,
derabbanan, it's not דאורייתא. dioraita. And תוספות Tosafot says, no, it is
דאורייתא. dioraita. He gives all of the proofs for it. There's many
גמרות Gemarot about it. But one of his proofs is this גמרא,
Gemara, because this גמרא Gemara we're talking at a דאורייתא dioraita level.
Since we say מין במינו min b'mino goes by רוב rov and
we know we never go by רוב rov in practice, we always
go by sixty, one in sixty, so he says we're talking here
at a דאורייתא dioraita level, and nevertheless we say taste is an
issue by מין באינו מינו. min b'eino mino. So תוספות Tosafot proves
from this גמרא Gemara that מין באינו מינו min b'eino mino is
that taste, טעם כעיקר ta'am k'ikar is דאורייתא. dioraita. Okay, so that's
a nice wrap-up of everything we just said. ופליגא דרבי אלעזר. u'pliga
d'Rabbi Elazar. Now back to, remember the statement of ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish yesterday? ריש לקיש Resh Lakish said that when you have three
איסורים, issurim, okay, you have or two, maybe depending on your גירסא,
girsa, but we'll say now for three, you have three different איסורים,
issurim, פיגול נותר וטמא, pigul, notar, v'tamei, that the two every two
outweighs the third and if you eat it you have not eaten
a כזית k'zayit of איסור issur because איסורין מבטלין זה את זה.
issurin mevatlin zeh et zeh. Even though it's all meat, okay,
and even though they're all things that are forbidden, nevertheless, there's a
majority of not kosher is מבטל mevattel איסור. issur. But non-נבלה neveilah
is מבטל mevattel נבלה neveilah even though the non-נבלה neveilah is אסור
assur for some different reason. So that was a principle of you
can even have ביטול bitul by איסור issur and איסור issur as
long as they're different איסורים. issurim. Okay, but that argues on רבי
אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. דאמר רבי אלעזר—excuse d'amar Rabbi Elazar me, רבי אלעזר—because
Rabbi Elazar רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says, כשם שאין מצות מבטלות זו
את זו, k'shem she'ein mitzvot mevatlot zo et zo, the same way
מצוות mitzvot are not מבטל mevattel one the other—now how do you
know that? We'll get to that—כך אין איסורין מבטלין זה את זה.
kach ein issurin mevatlin zeh et zeh. Similarly by איסור, issur, if
you have multiple איסורים issurim in your mouth and you do not
say that they negate one another and ביטול bitul takes effect. You
need היתר hetter against איסור issur for ביטול bitul to take effect.
Or in our case, like neutral wine against קרבן korban blood. But
you can't have איסור issur and איסור issur and everything is off-limits
and say that they're מבטל mevattel one another. Okay, now he says
that based on the principle that you wouldn't say it by מצוות.
mitzvot. Well where's an example by מצוות mitzvot that things would be
mixed up together? Like if I'm wearing טלית tallit and
תפילין tefillin and and I don't know shaking a לולב, lulav, assuming
I wear טלית tallit תפילין tefillin on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, right?
Obviously they're not מבטל mevattel זו את זו zo et zo because
each one is distinct. So what would be a similar scenario where
I might say ביטול bitul would work and it doesn't? So the
answer is I'm at the wrong חג. chag. Don't talk about סוכות,
Sukkot, talk about פסח. Pesach. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
מאן שמעת ליה דאמר אין מצות מבטלות זו את זו. man shamat
leh d'amar ein mitzvot mevatlot zo et zo.
Where does רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar get the idea that מצוות mitzvot
are not מבטל mevattel one another and that he bases on that
to say the same is true about איסור? issur? Who says that?
הלל! Hillel! It's הלל. Hillel. היא דתניא, hee d'tanya, אמרו עליו על
הלל הזקן, amru alav al Hillel Hazaken, they said about הלל Hillel
the elder, שהיה כורכן בבת אחת ואוכלן, shehayah korchan b'vat achat v'ochlan,
that not only what everybody says על מצות ומרורים יאכלוהו, al matzot
u'merorim yochluhu, that you have to eat it together with מצה matzah
and מרור, maror, but not everybody reads it like הלל Hillel that
it's a sandwich. You could read it as you take a little
bit of of קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, then you eat a little
מרור, maror, then you eat a little מצה. matzah. That's eating them
together. But הלל Hillel says you ממש mamash wrap them together and
it's as one thing. שהיה כורכן ואוכלן, Shehayah korchan v'ochlan, משום שנאמר...
mishum shene'emar... because it says על מצות ומרורים יאכלו al matzot umrorim
yochlu and he reads that as literally as a sandwich. Everybody of
course knows this from the הגדה. Haggadah. So there you are, and
you are eating them, and you are chewing them together. You know,
when they're just wrapped as a sandwich, they're not מבטל mevatel because
each one is distinct. But then you chew them all together in
your mouth, and you swallow it. So why don't you say, well,
you know, if in that swallow you have more מצה matzah and
מרור marror than you have פסח, pesach, then you haven't eaten the
קרבן פסח. korban pesach. And you don't say that. You say that
מצות mitzvos are not מבטל mevatel זו את זו. zu es zu.
Each one remains distinct and or each one retains its identity, and
you are eating all three. And the same way that's true, it
would be true of איסור issur as well. תוספות Tosafot here just
points out אמרו על הלל שהיה כורכן בבת אחת. amru al Hillel
shehaya korchan bevats achas. תוספות Tosafot says בזמן הבית, bizman habayit, at
the time of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, which was actually when
הלל Hillel lived,
ששלשתן דאורייתא, sheshloshtan d'oraysa, that they're all דאורייתא. d'oraysa. Okay, and the
reason he says that is because because,
you know, תוספות Tosafot says the reason we eat מרור marror before
we do כורך korech is because מרור marror is a דרבנן derabbanan
and the reason we eat מרור marror separate from מצה matzah is
they're each at a different level. מצה's Matzah דאורייתא, d'oraysa, מרור's marror
דרבנן, derabbanan, and כורך korech is a זכר. zecher. And if you
were to somehow like try to do your מרור marror together with
your כורך, korech, then actually, you know, the מרור marror and the
מצה matzah would be מבטל mevatel one another because they are at
different levels. So the principle that אין מצות מבטלות זו את זו
ein mitzvos mevatlos zu es zu is only if they're all recognized
at the same level as a מצוה, mitzvah, but if one is
recognized as a דאורייתא d'oraysa מצוה, mitzvah, then a דרבנן derabbanan מצוה
mitzvah doesn't count as a מצוה mitzvah in that context and therefore
ביטול bittul could occur. Okay, but at least when they're all at
the same level, ביטול bittul does not occur. All right, very good.
Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says top of עט עמוד ב. Ayin
Tes Amud Beis. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. So now that's done with
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish about about איסורין מבטלין זה את זה issurin
mevatlin zeh es zeh and it's done with the general principles about
מין במינו min bemino and אינו מינו eino mino and טעם ta'am
and appearances. So very, very critical principles in ביטול. bittul. Okay. תנו
רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, our rabbis taught: חוסן של זב וזבה. chosin shel
zav vezavah. If you have a, you know, a chamber pot that
was made out of pottery, pot, anyway that was used for a
זב zav and a זבה zavah used it to urinate in, and
the urine of a זב zav and a זבה zavah is an
אב הטומאה, av hatumah, and because it's pottery, it's porous and it
got absorbed in the pot.
So so that is טמא. tamei. Now since it's not בעין ba'ayin
right now, so it's not בטול batul because if you were to
put it in an oven, which is the part of that משנה,
mishnah, then the urine would come back out and and therefore and
therefore it would be טמא. tamei. So you have to be concerned
basically you treat it as טמא tamei because you have to be
concerned that the urine is going to come out either if you
put it in an oven or if you use other liquids with
it or put other liquids in it, you know, the it will
the it will come out through the pores back into the liquids
and therefore it is a problem.
Okay. פעם ראשונה ושניה טמא. paam rishonah ushniyah tamei. If you washed
it out once or twice, it's still going to be טמא tamei
because it doesn't still get all the urine out of the pores.
Okay. שלישי טהור. shlishi tahor. Three times it's טהור. tahor. Now by
the way this is interesting. Normally we say vessels only absorb with
heat, but this is pottery which is porous and that can absorb
even cold, that actually comes up in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah about
wine. Okay. By the third time you say that it will get
all the urine out and it is now טהור, tahor, you do
not have to worry about any urine left absorbed in the pot.
במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim, when is that true? שנתן לתוכו
מים, shenatan letocho mayim, if you put water in it. אבל לא
נתן לתוכו מים, aval lo natan letocho mayim, if you didn't put
water, and רש״י Rashi says meaning you used it for urine two
or three times afterwards, not of a זב zav and a זבה,
zavah, normal urine is טהור, tahor, אפילו עשירית טמא, afilu asiris tamei,
even ten times it is טמא. tamei. Why? So you could say
maybe it doesn't do as good of a job as getting it
out of the pores. But what רש״י Rashi says and what the
גמרא Gemara assumes is no, because in that case you are afraid
that tiny little משהו mashehu of the urine will still come out,
you know, even if you even after multiple uses from other things,
and then if it's urine in urine, it won't be בטל. batel.
And according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, מין במינו, min bemino, and
therefore it will still be טמא. tamei. So if it's water, then
any tiny amount that comes out after three times is going to
be בטל. batel. But if it's urine that you're using, any tiny
amount, מין במינו min bemino won't be בטל batel and that is
the problem. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer,
שלישי אף על פי שלא נתן לתוכו מים טהור. shlishi af al
pi shelo natan letocho mayim tahor. No,
once you do it three times it's fine, okay, even because מין
במינו min bemino would be בטל. batel. So that's at least the
way the גמרא Gemara understands this debate about and the problem is
a tiny trace amounts will still come out in the third time
and if you use urine for according to the תנא קמא, Tanna
Kamma, מין במינו min bemino is not בטל. batel. So the גמרא
Gemara says that. מאן שמעת ליה דאמר מין במינו לא בטיל? man
shamas lei d'amar min bemino lo batil? רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So
this is רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, he is the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma because he is the one and that's why using it for
urine the third time would not be good.
I'll ask you on this. Here's a very analogous debate with רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that he doesn't seem to sort of say the
same position. What does he say? פשתן שטוותו נדה. Pishtan she-tavaso nidda.
If you have a נדה Nidda that has spun flax, and you
know, you would use your mouth and your saliva when you were
spinning flax, and the saliva of a נדה Nidda is also an
אב הטומאה. av hatumah.
So מסיטו טהור. mesito tahor. So if it is dry, even though
she spun it, now it's dry, so you know where then then
if you move it you are טהור tahor because even if there's
some saliva absorbed in, it's not going to be coming out and
therefore and it's not out now, so it is טהור. tahor. ואם
היה לח מסיטו טמא. V'im haya lach mesito tamei. But however if
it was still wet from when she had you know wet it
with her mouth, then there's still is the saliva on it and
if you move it you are טמא, tamei, you've moved the saliva
of of of a נדה Nidda משום משקה פיה mishum mashkeh piha
because of the the liquid in her mouth, the saliva. רבי יהודה
אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, Rabbi Yehuda says אף הרוק במים טמא משום
משקה פיה. Af harok b'mayim tamei mishum mashkeh piha. Rabbi Yehuda says
even if you went ahead and you it was not wet from
the original you know saliva of her mouth, it had dried off,
but now you got it wet again with water, the the fact
that you're now adding water and getting it wet again that will
draw out the saliva that is absorbed into the thread into and
therefore again it will be טמא tamei because now the saliva is
no longer absorbed and it is now בעין, b'ayin, it is mixed
with the water now that you've washed it with. And the גמרא
Gemara says ואפילו טובא, v'afillu tuva, even even if you have like
rinsed it many many times it is still going to be a
problem. So there you have explicitly רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. And the
גמרא Gemara says how does this work? Because the original opinion said
that when you rinse out the you know the urine of the
chamber pot you know many times it's going to be טהור tahor
according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. And here you have רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda saying that if you you know that if you wet
the the fiber what do you, the the flax, the thread,
even no matter how you know no matter how many times you
wet it and it dried and you wet it and it dried,
it's still going to be טמא. tamei. Why is that? So you
might realize that there's a very easy answer here which we will
get back to, but let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay,
so that's the question. In the case of the chamber pot which
we identified with רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it said you by the
third time it's okay, and here by the thread רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is explicitly talking and presumably even after multiple times when you
get it wet it's still a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says
אמר רב פפא שאני רוק דקריר, Amar Rav Pappa shani rok d'karir,
no spit is different, spit is like adhesive. So you know the
spit will stay absorbed into the thread more than the urine will
stay present in in the pores of the pottery. So the urine
will come out already by three times whereas the spit won't fully
come out and therefore even multiple times it is still going to
be a problem. Now, you might realize that there's a much easier
answer. The reason the גמרא Gemara identified the whole case of the
chamber pot with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was because in the case
of urine he says even multiple times it's a problem because there
will still be trace amounts and מין במינו לא בטיל. min b'mino
lo batil. That seems to be how the גמרא Gemara was understanding.
Well if that's true, that totally explains רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about
the thread and about the flax. No matter how many times you
wet it, it's water, it's saliva with you know with water, מין
במינו לא בטיל, min b'mino lo batil, and that's why it actually
works perfectly. So the אחרונים acharonim ask this question, you know the
best one answer is well maybe he thinks saliva and water are
not the same substance, which is bizarre. Anyway it is I really
don't know what to say but at least the אחרונים acharonim do
ask the question but it is quite strange. Okay so that is
the end of that whole discussion of מין במינו min b'mino and
ביטול. bittul. Now we get on to the end of the משנה.
Mishnah. נתערב בדם פסול ישפך לאמה. Nit'arev b'dam pasul yishafech l'amah. So
it says if the blood here gets mixed up not with water,
not with wine, not with blood of a you know a non-sanctified
animal, but it got mixed up with the blood of either of
of something that is פסול, pasul, you know an animal that I
don't know could be פיגול, piggul, could be whatever some other פסול
psul happened to the animal, בעל מום, ba'al mum, or with
or with the blood of תמצית. tamtzit. After you שחט shacht the
animal, the first you know the spurting of blood initially is called
the life blood but after a while the remainder blood is called
blood of תמצית. tamtzit.
And that you cannot use to put on the מזבח mizbeach because
that is not the blood that holds the life. Okay so obviously
it's all the same blood but that's at least how חז"ל Chazal
understood it. Now
so so it says if it gets mixed up with with those
bloods, rather than sprinkle it we actually say spill it out, okay,
which is strange because it shouldn't be בטל. batel. We know... Already
that it's not בטל. batel. So why do you have to spill
it out? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. במאי קמיפלגי?
Bemai kamiflagi? What are they debating? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, no,
you can actually still use it. So what's that debate about? אמר
זביד Amar Zvid בגוזרין גזירה במקדש קמיפלגי. b'gozin gezira b'mikdash kamiflagi. The
question is do we make a גזירה gezira in the בית המקדש?
Beis HaMikdash? Often we are told, you know, that there's not שבות
במקדש, shvus b'mikdash, there are דרבנן's rabbonan relating to שבת Shabbos in
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash because כהנים kohanim are careful, okay, do
we make other גזירות gezeros in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and
particularly here where the cost will be you'll be having to throw
out a sacrifice, you know, you'll be having to waste a sacrifice
if you spill it out. Now what's the concern? What's the גזירה?
gezira? Right, what are we afraid might happen? Okay, so let's take
a look.
דמר סבר גוזרין ומר סבר לא גוזרין. Demar savar gozun umar savar
lo gozun. One holds you do make a גזירה gezira and one
holds you don't. What's the גזירה? gezira? So רש"י Rashi says the
גזירה gezira is is that it'll get if we allow you to
use it when the kosher when the קרבן korban blood is not
בטל, batel, you might come to use it when the קרבן korban
blood is בטל. batel. Okay, so and that's why. So in the
earlier cases where it gets mixed up with wine, with water, with
non-sanctified animals, those are all not common cases. So we're not afraid
that if we let you use it it'll come to be a
case where you know where you might come where it might in
one case be בטל batel and you'll use it otherwise. But when
it gets mixed up with the other blood that is coming out
of the neck of the animal or with a non-a פסול posul
animal, those are common occurrences in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, maybe
we don't want to allow ביטול bittul to work there excuse me,
not ביטול, bittul, maybe
we don't maybe I said it in the reverse. Anyway, you need
it to not be בטל, batel, right, in order to keep on
using it. Anyway, maybe you want to not sort of any mixture
you want to assume it is loses its identity and is בטל
batel because those are relatively common cases and therefore you don't want
to allow it so you'll always assume that it is בטל batel
again it's funny here being בטל batel is the problem and therefore
you spill it out. That's the debate. Okay, רב פפא אמר Rav
Pappa amar and רב פפא Rav Pappa says no, דכולי עלמא גוזרין.
d'chulei alma gozin. Everybody would say in principle you would make a
גזירה gezira by a common case and you would therefore you know
not allow not say the blood is still present and not be
able to use it because there'll be times when it will be
בטל. batel. והכא
בדם התמצית מותר לרבות דם הנפש קמיפלגי. V'hacha b'dam hatamsis matre l'rabos
ha dam hanefesh kamiflagi. The question is is this a rare or
not so rare occurrence. Okay, you know are we concerned that if
we let you use it when there's some blood that's not the
soul blood, you know, mixed in, that you'll come to be you
know that that could lead to a case where there is so
much of the non-soul blood that it's בטל batel and can't be
used. So how common is it that there will be so much
quantity of like the non-soul blood you know that this shall be
that this would be that that this would be a problem that
it actually would be בטל. batel. That's the debate. Okay, מר סבר
שכיח Mar savar shchiach one says you know that can happen, it's
possible by the time you catch the soul blood and then all
the blood that comes afterwards and there could be cases when it
would be בטל batel so we always have to be concerned about
those cases that is something that could happen. מר סבר לא שכיח
Mar savar lo shchiach and the other one holds that it's not
so common. Okay, so everybody agrees that when it would be a
common case we would make the גזירה, gezira, but the question is
does you know is the case of the non-soul blood a common
case that it might lead to ביטול bittul and ביטול bittul would
be a problem here.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
בשלמא לרב פפא היינו דתני נתערב בדם הפסולים ישפך לאמה בדם התמצית
ישפך לאמה. Bishlama l'Rav Pappa hainu d'sani nisarav b'dam hapsulim yishafech l'amah
b'dam hatamsis yishafech l'amah. The משנה Mishnah separated the two cases. It
says if it got mixed up with invalid blood spill it out,
spill it in the gutter. If it got mixed up with blood
of the תמצית, tamsis, spill it in the blood gutter. And רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no you can throw it. So because it
said it as two separate cases, the simple reason why did it
break up those cases was to say that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
is only debating the second one. The first one דם פסולים dam
psulim I agree, spill it out. Okay that it makes sense to
make a גזירה gezira that's a common case there could be a
lot of פסולים psulim around it could be that it'll be בטל
batel spill that out. The second case דם תמצית dam tamsis I'm
disagreeing says רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, I think that's not a common
case where ביטול bittul will occur and therefore I say you do
not need to spill it out. So it makes sense that we
separated it because they're only debating the question of דם תמצית. dam
tamsis. אלא לרב זביד לערבינהו ולתנינהו Ella Rav Zvid l'arvinu v'lisninu but
according to רב זביד, Rav Zvid, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer rejects both
concerns, he says we don't make גזירות gezeros and therefore I'm not
concerned about either case. So why did you separate it into two
separate cases? It should have joined them all as one case. So
the גמרא Gemara says קשיא. kashya. All right, that's difficult. All right,
very good. Anyway, that's how the גמרא Gemara explains it. Now two
points. First of all, I assume that you know when is a
case that we don't allow you to use it if it got
mixed up, you know, would that even be a case where the
kosher blood was a majority? Presumably not, if a drop of דם
תמצית dam tamsis got mixed up, right, then
at the verge of being בטל, batel, so that's not so clear.
That's just one point. But the other more interesting point that is
what תוספות Tosafot says. תוספות Tosafot says, why did the גמרא Gemara
have to go to them debating a גזירה? gezeira? Why didn't תוספות
Tosafot just say this is the old debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer and the חכמים? Chachamim? Right? That the חכמים Chachamim say we
are, you know, we don't want you to use it if it's
got non, if it's got, if it's got פסול pasul blood, we
don't want that going on the מזבח. Mizbeiach.
And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no, I allow it to go
on the מזבח Mizbeiach because you look at it as if it's
water and that's the debate. So תוספות Tosafot says, well you know,
I'm elaborating here a little bit. If the חכמים Chachamim were afraid
that non-kosher blood going on the מזבח, Mizbeiach, then why wouldn't they
also have a problem with it being, you know, a what do
you call it, with it being a, what do you call it,
a non, like a non-קרבן korban getting mixed up, or wine, or
water? So תוספות Tosafot says, ah well we can answer that, right?
Because we can say that when it's something that's completely not fit
for the מזבח, Mizbeiach, wine, water, a non-sanctified animal,
putting it on the מזבח Mizbeiach is not a big deal or
you could look at it as though it's water. It's not problematic
because it doesn't belong there. You know, of course you could say
maybe it's particularly problematic because it's חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. But you
could also say that when I intentionally don't want to be מקריב
makriv it and I'm looking at it as if it's water and
it doesn't even belong on the מזבח, Mizbeiach, so I ignore it.
But when you're dealing with דם פסולים dam psulim or דם תמצית,
dam tamtzis, which is from a sanctified animal, it's just that it's
not the right blood, there maybe there's a specific problem of putting
it on the מזבח Mizbeiach and that's why the חכמים Chachamim say
it's no good. And that's why רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it
is good because he consistently says you look at it as if
it's water. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot raises that as a possible read
of the משנה, mishna, but it's not the read that the גמרא
Gemara is taking. So then טאקע tako why does the גמרא Gemara
not explain it that way? So תוספות Tosafot has two explanations. One
is because רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is not, does not have his
catchphrase. If that were, if that was the case רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer should say רואה אני כאילו הוא מים. ro'eh ani k'ilu hu
mayim. If that's why he was allowing it. So it sounds like
it's based on something else. The other answer is that maybe if
they were only debating the case of פסול pasul blood, that would
make sense. But because they're also debating the case of the דם
תמצית, dam tamtzis, תוספות Tosafot says, you know, it might come from
an animal that's a קרבן, korban, but it's no longer, no more
belongs on the מזבח Mizbeiach than blood of a non-sanctified animal or
than wine or than water. Okay, it's just a different type of
a substance. So the fact that they're even debating the issue of
the דם תמצית, dam tamtzis, you know, תוספות Tosafot says that would
not be a fundamental problem of putting it on the מזבח. Mizbeiach.
That's no different than the case of blood of a חיה, chaya,
and therefore it obviously is based on a גזירה gezeira and not
on the fundamental problematics of putting it on the מזבח. Mizbeiach. Okay,
let's take a look at the next משנה mishna where this discussion
continues. דם תמימים בדם בעלי מומין. dam tmimim b'dam ba'alei mumin. You
get blood of
animal unblemished with blood of an animal that's blemished. It's sort of
like the דם פסולים dam psulim of the previous משנה. mishna. Let's
see how this is different. ישפך לאמה, yishapech l'amah, you spill it
out, and nobody debates that. Even for example, even presumably רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer doesn't say that you can go ahead and use it.
Which is quite fascinating. So again it seems, you know, seems like
for some reason רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is looking at it as
if it's water. I don't know, might not be relevant here or
because presumably this is a case about גזירה. gezeira. It goes back
to תוספות's Tosafot point. Somehow in this case of the bloods, we're
focusing in on fundamentally it can be done and there's a גזירה
gezeira issue and not that there's a fundamental problem. That seems to
be the approach here. Okay, so this is very similar to exactly
the same ruling before without רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer debating it about
spilling it into the אמה amah because it's another variation of דם
פסולים. dam psulim. כוס בכוסות. kos b'kosos. Now let's talk about something
a little different. Okay, you have one, you know, cup, whatever, one
basin of blood that you caught the blood of an animal without
a blemish and one that you caught of the blood of an
animal with a blemish, okay, and you don't know which is which.
All right, so this should sound familiar. It's like getting mixed up
the limbs of a בעל מום ba'al mum etc. that goes on
the מזבח Mizbeiach etc. רבי אליעזר אומר אם קרב כוס אחד יקרבו
כל הכוסות. Rabbi Eliezer omer im kariv kos echad yikrevu kol hakosos.
If one is offered, then you can offer the rest. You can
assume that the one problematic one was offered. Okay,
and maybe it is because fundamentally he holds you could look at
it as if it's water, you know, again, like why does he
allow You know, why does he allow that to work? Maybe fundamentally
he holds that it's בטל, batel, it goes בטל ברוב, batel berov,
but some reason is that he fundamentally holds it's not a problem,
which allows him then to pretend, live in this fiction, that if
one of them was offered up we can pretend that it was
the one that was a problem. That only works if fundamentally ביטול
bitul works here or fundamentally you have a principle of you look
at it as if it's water and that is what allows it.
Okay.
וחכמים אומרים, V'Chachamim omrim, and the חכמים Chachamim say, אפילו קרבו כולן
חוץ מאחד מהן ישפך לאמה, afilu karvu kulan chutz me'echad mehen yishafach
l'amah, even if all of them were thrown on the מזבח mizbeach
and only one was left, so it's almost definite that the פסול
pasul one was already done? Nope, this still might be the פסול
pasul one and you have to spill it out. Okay, that's very
of course similar to other debates that we have seen.
Now, shifting gears a little bit.
הניתנים למטה שנתערבו בניתנים למעלה. Hanitannim lemata shenisarvu benitannim lemala. You have
the blood of a חטאת chatas that got mixed up with the
blood of some of the קרבנות korbanot that go on the below
the midpoint of the מזבח, mizbeach, an עולה, olah, שלמים, shelamim, whatever.
רבי אליעזר אומר, יתן למעלה Rabbi Eliezer omer yiten lemala, ורואה אני
את התחתונים מלמעלה כאילו הם מים. v'roeh ani es hatachtonim milmala ke'ilu
hem mayim, We're back to looking at it as if it's water.
So when you actually have a type of a מין במינו, min
bemino, you know, getting mixed up, right, then רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
excuse me, not a מין במינו, min bemino, when you actually have
them as this is a different concept in כשרות kashrut which is
called, the ראשונים rishonim come up with this term, יבש ביבש או
לח בלח. yavesh b'yavesh o lach b'lach. יבש ביבש yavesh b'yavesh is
distinct items, you can't identify which is which, but it's not that
everything gets dispersed, and לח בלח lach b'lach is it gets dispersed.
So basically with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer he's much more lenient, he
has this idea of רואה כאילו הם מים, roeh ke'ilu hem mayim,
but when it is יבש ביבש, yavesh b'yavesh, when it is one
limb in other limbs, one basin of blood with another basin of
blood, he doesn't say רואה אני כאילו הם מים. roeh ani ke'ilu
hem mayim. He says I'm going to wait till one was done.
Once one was done then you can assume that that was the
problematic and now you can do the rest. If one wasn't done,
you can't use it. For some reason he does not allow the
רואה כאילו הם מים. roeh ke'ilu hem mayim. Okay, maybe because if
you're throwing them separately, you could throw them separately and then you
know you would only be throwing the פסול pasul one. So therefore,
maybe רואה כאילו הם מים roeh ke'ilu hem mayim is when you're
always definitely doing the kosher and the פסול pasul one is just
mixed up in them. Okay, so in the case of יבש ביבש,
yavesh b'yavesh, you know, in the case of limbs or of כוסות
kosot or whatever, he says no, you cannot use it לכתחילה. lechatchila.
If one was done, now you can do the rest. However, in
the case of לח בלח, lach b'lach, blood getting mixed up with
blood, you know, then he says go ahead and you're definitely doing
the kosher with every sprinkling of blood, there's some פסול pasul mixed
up in it, but I see it as if it's מים. mayim.
Okay, so that's what he says here too. You do ahead and
you sprinkle it, if it's the ones above and the ones below.
So, where were we? רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer, יתן למעלה,
so you go ahead and you first you do the corners of
the מזבח mizbeach that you would do of the חטאת, chatas, ורואה
אני את התחתונים מלמעלה כאילו הם מים, and therefore the fact even
though there is some blood mixed that's an עולה, olah, you pretend
you act as if that is
water. Okay. ויחזור ויתן למטה, V'yachzor v'yiten lemata, and then you go
ahead and you do below. Now why doesn't he say when you
do below and you look at the blood of the חטאת chatas
as if it's water? So רש"י Rashi says no, because the blood
of the חטאת chatas when you're putting it below the line, that
could constitute just the שפיכת שיריים, shfichas shirayim, the spilling out of
the remnant of the blood of the חטאת. chatas. Okay, so you
first do it above, the חטאת chatas blood is good, the trace
parts of the עולה olah blood mixed in or whatever the fifty
percent doesn't matter, but there's definitely חטאת chatas blood, the fifty percent
of the עולה olah blood mixed in is water, you pretend as
if it's water, then you do it below, the עולה olah blood
is good for זריקה, zrika, and the חטאת chatas blood is the
spilling of the
שיריים. shirayim. וחכמים אומרים ישפך לאמה, V'Chachamim omrim yishafach l'amah, the חכמים
Chachamim say you spill it out. Okay, so again, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says when it is a לח בלח lach b'lach go ahead
and do it and look at the problematic one as if it's
water, and again presumably I let you do it לכתחילה lechatchila because
you're always doing the right thing, it's just the bad thing is
mixed up together with it. When it's יבש ביבש yavesh b'yavesh I'm
not going to let you do it until one is done and
then we can pretend that that was the problematic and now you
can do the rest.
וחכמים אומרים ישפך לאמה, V'Chachamim omrim yishafach l'amah, ואם לא נמלך, v'im
lo nimlach, if the כהן kohen didn't ask permission, then ונעשה כשר,
v'na'asah kasher, and he did it, it was כשר. kasher. Okay, the
חכמים Chachamim do not want you to put עולה olah blood up
on the top of the מזבח mizbeach where חטאת chatas blood belongs,
not exactly clear what איסור issur that is, but they don't want
you doing that, so they'll say spill it all out, but if
you did not ask and you did it, it's כשר. kasher. חטאת
Chatas blood went on top, the עולה olah blood went on the
bottom, even though it was all mixed, so בדיעבד bedieved it is
going to be כשר. kasher. Okay. Top of דף פ"א עמוד
א'. daf pei aleph amud aleph. הניתנים במתנה אחת שנתערבו בניתנים במתנה
אחת. Hanitannim b'matanah achat shenisarvu benitannim b'matanah achat. Now let's say you
have... would be בכור bechor and מעשר ma'aser and פסח. pesach. So
let's say their bloods all got mixed up, easy, יינתנו במתנה אחת,
yinatnu bematana achat, you do the one application and it counts for
all three because there's some of all the bloods in it. מתן
ארבע במתן ארבע, Matan arba bematan arba, you got blood of, you
know, of a four with blood of a four. Now that could
be חטאת chatat with חטאת. chatat. You know, רש"י Rashi says it
means עולה olah with שלמים shlamim because, and four meaning two that
are four, the two diagonal. Okay, but יינתנו במתן ארבע, yinatnu bematan
arba, you go ahead and you go, you do the two diagonal
and you got both the עולה olah and the שלמים. shlamim. You
know, the bloods were mixed up but they both, they both worked,
so it's fine. That's all easy when it's the same.
Now, מתן ארבע במתן אחת. matan arba bematan achat. Let's say you
got the blood of an עולה olah mixed up with the blood
of a, you know, בכור. bechor. And the עולה olah is two
at opposite corners, which we'll call four, and the בכור bechor is
one. So what do you do? So remember the הלכה halacha is
that בדיעבד bedi'avad if you only do one, it accounts. So you
have two choices here: do all four and the ones will get,
and the thing that was one gets extra, or do one and
the thing that should have been four gets less.
רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer יינתנו במתן ארבע, yinatnu bematan arba,
you do it with four. Okay, obviously because Rabbi Eliezer says you
look at the, at the one that doesn't belong like it's water.
So you do it with four. The one, you know, that deserved
only the one was done with the first corner, and the second
corner, you know, the עולה olah counts and the בכור bechor you
look at it as if it's water. So you do the bigger
one, you do the four and the problematic one you just look
at as if it's water for the corner that it does not,
that it should not be done at. That's Rabbi Eliezer. רבי
יהושע אומר Rabbi Yehoshua omer יינתנו במתנה אחת. yinatnu bematana achat. No,
you only do the one corner. I'm not prepared to look at
it as if it's water. I won't put blood on, at the
wrong place of the מזבח. mizbeach. So I'm only going to do
the one corner and בדיעבד bedi'avad you'll be יוצא yotze even for
the עולה olah even if you only did one. Okay. אמר לו
רבי אליעזר, Amar lo Rabbi Eliezer, Rabbi Eliezer said to Rabbi Yehoshua,
הרי הוא עובר על בל תגרע. harei hu over al bal tigra.
You're transgressing you shall not decrease from it, like לא תוסיפו על
הדבר אשר אנכי מצוה אתכם ולא תגרעו ממנו. lo tosifu al hadavar
asher anochi metzaveh etchem velo tigre'u mimenu. Don't add to what I
am commanding you and don't take away from it. The simple sense
of that פסוק pasuk is don't add to the corpus of מצוות,
mitzvot, you know, and don't claim that there's less than they are.
But the way חז"ל Chazal understand it, it's off, don't change the
structure of a מצוה. mitzvah. Don't take חמישה מינים chamisha minim of
a לולב, lulav, don't have five, you know, compartments of your תפילין.
tefillin. So that's בל תוסיף. bal tosif. בל תגרע Bal tigra is
a little more of a challenge. How can you be עובר over
on בל תגרע? bal tigra? Because anytime you do less than you're
supposed to, are you עובר over on בל תגרע? bal tigra? You
just didn't do the מצוה. mitzvah. If I take שלושה מינים shlosha
minim of a לולב, lulav, if I put on תפילין tefillin that
has three compartments, was I עובר over on בל תגרע bal tigra
or was I just not doing the מצוה? mitzvah? You might need
to start with the מצוה mitzvah and then add to it to
be עובר over on בל תוסיף. bal tosif. So how can you
ever be עובר over on בל תגרע? bal tigra? So here's one
of the places you can be עובר over on בל תגרע, bal
tigra, because you did it, you were supposed to do four, you
know, or two opposite corners, and you only did one. So you
still did the מצוה, mitzvah, but you did it in a lesser
way and it's something that is quantifiable, has numbers, not just qualitative
less, quantifiable less. You went from four or two that are four
to one. So you did less and you still did the מצוה.
mitzvah. That's בל תגרע. bal tigra. Now, I should say that it's
a big חידוש chiddush that it's בל תגרע bal tigra anyway, beside,
you know, because it's not like, it's not like, you know, it's
like how much is there a מעשה מצוה ma'aseh mitzvah of throwing
the blood or is this just how the עבודה avodah of the
קרבן korban is supposed to be done. But anyway, that's what he
says. He says, so Rabbi Eliezer says if you're only going to
do one, you're going to be עובר over on בל תגרע. bal
tigra. אמר לו רבי יהושע, Amar lo Rabbi Yehoshua, so Rabbi Yehoshua
said back to him, הרי הוא עובר על בל תוסיף. harei hu
over al bal tosif. According to you, you say I'm עובר over
בל תגרע bal tigra with the blood of the עולה, olah, you're
עובר over בל תוסיף bal tosif with the blood of the בכור.
bechor. You're doing it on an extra corner. Okay, now Rabbi Eliezer
has an easy answer, which is I look at it as if
it's water. But אמר לו רבי אליעזר, amar lo Rabbi Eliezer, but
Rabbi Eliezer, לא נאמר בל תוסיף אלא כשהוא בעצמו. lo ne'emar bal
tosif ela keshehu be'atzmo. No, it's not בל תוסיף bal tosif is
if I took the blood of the בכור bechor when it was
distinct and put it on the corner. Here that it's mixed up
with the blood of, you know, the עולה, olah, I mean, what
I'm doing I'm doing for the sake of the עולה. olah. I'm
not doing a separate act on the blood of the, of the
בכור. bechor. And therefore it's not בל תוסיף. bal tosif. I'm not
doing something special with the blood of the בכור. bechor. Fundamentally what
I'm doing is with the blood of the עולה. olah. Now this
could be a way of, of his point that you look at
it as if it's water, but it could be he's saying even
forget that. I personally look at the blood that you don't, doesn't
belong there as if it's water. Even you that are not prepared
to look at it as if it's water, okay, I'm not doing
an act of specifically of adding to the בכור. bechor. Fundamentally I'm
doing, I'm doing this for the sake of the עולה. olah. the
עולה olah and therefore it is not בל תוסיף bal tosif of
the בכור. bechor. אמר ליה Amar leh רבי יהושע, Rebbe Yehoshua, רבי
יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua said back, לא נאמר lo ne'emar בל תגרע bal
tigra כשהוא בעצמו k'sheu be'atzmo so don't tell me that I'm over
on בל תגרע, bal tigra, right? I'm the reason I'm abstaining from
doing the other thing is because I don't want because it's got
the blood of the בכור bechor mixed into it. So I'm not
actively choosing to do it less. Now, רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer I
think could can well let's just finish it up. ועוד אמר רבי
יהושע Ve'od amar Rebbe Yehoshua and רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua thinks his
position is better. Why? כשנתת עברת על בל תוסיף עשית מעשה בידך.
Keshenatata avarta al bal tosif asita ma'aseh beyadecha. So you have to
choose between extra or less. I'd rather do less and do a
sin of omission than do more and do a sin of commission.
If you went ahead and did it on the other corner, you're
over on בל תוסיף bal tosif and you've actively done it. כשלא
נתת Keshelo natata when you don't when you only do one corner,
עברת על בל תגרע avarta al bal tigra you're over on בל
תגרע bal tigra ולא עשית מעשה בידך velo asita ma'aseh beyadecha but
you only did it passively. So for רבי יהושע, Rebbe Yehoshua, he
presumably understands רבי אליעזר's Rebbe Eliezer's point that, you know, כשהוא בעצמו
k'sheu be'atzmo sort of as like, well, you're forced into this circumstance.
To which רבי יהושע's Rebbe Yehoshua's answer is, if you're forced into
it, I'd rather therefore not do something problematic and what's problematic is
passive because and I have no choice, rather than to actively do
something problematic just because I have no choice. So I'd rather do
the one and just passively be over on בל תגרע. bal tigra.
But I think רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer could be saying something different.
He's not just saying you don't have a choice. It's somewhat similar
to his point of you look at it as if it's water.
He's saying it's not בל תוסיף bal tosif because you're not doing
it to expand the מצוה mitzvah of בכור. bechor. You're doing it
in order to do the מצוה mitzvah of עולה. olah. And that's
you can't say that by בל תגרע. bal tigra. Because by בל
תגרע bal tigra at the end of the day you did the
מצוה mitzvah in a lesser way. You did it only one and
not two. I would rather do extra and it not be defined
as בל תוסיף bal tosif because I'm doing it for the sake
of the other one than do less and objectively I have done
the מצוה mitzvah in a lesser way. That could be the position
of רבי אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. Okay, we will pick up with this
tomorrow.